All right, so now
we're going to look
at thumbnail design basics.
And the first thing
I would encourage you
to do is just
to outsource design. I
have a huge course
teaching you photography and
Photoshop. The thing is,
it's a huge course
because there's so much
to learn about creating
images. So I would
highly recommend you outsource
design. What I'm going
to recommend we do
is when we're coming
up with our thumbnails,
we do this. So
this is how all
my thumbnails start. A
crappy doodle. You would
then send it to
your designer who would
hopefully make it look
better. But you do
need to know the
rules because a lot
of fun designers are
going to break them.
So let's look at
the basics of actual
creative from that design.
Now, the first thing
is just composition. So
there's this thing called
the rule of thirds
in its simplest form.
You just put stuff
where these lines intersect
so we can see
James here is on
the left and he's
intersecting on that line.
And you'll see a
lot of thumbnails do
exactly the same thing
where they're on the
left. And then text
is on the right.
And then James here
is on the right
and he's on this
intersecting line.
And then as you
can see, Dango and
Nisha and I can't
remember his name, are
on the right with
the thing on the
left. And then the
other option is we're
in the middle and
you can see James's
eyes are on the
line here. And if
we go and look
at these examples, all
of these are doing
the same person in
the middle text. So
really, your choice for
thumbnail design is pretty
simple. Put yourself on
the left, put yourself
on the right, put
yourself in the middle.
But I always go
on the right and
most people do because
we read left to
right. So if we're
using text and we
want the text to
stick out first, it
just makes sense. But
which one do you
use? Well, you try
different ones out until
you find the thing
that works. OK, so
the next thing you
need to understand is
contrast. So which ones
of these sticks out
to you first? What
do you notice? So
in this image, in
this style, I want
the text to get
attention. Now, this one
sure gets attention. The
problem is the green
makes it harder. To
read, right? And this
one kind of sticks
out. But this one
where it's just white
on black, it pops,
right? It sticks out
really fast. And that
is because of contrast.
So black and white
are the opposites. They
are the furthest point
of contrast you can
get. So when you're
designing things, what we
want to do is
we want to make
sure the thing that
we want to stick
out has contrast. So
it's separated from the
background. Although I do
like that orange one.
It's pretty good. So
here's some examples of
creators using contrast so
that their hero sticks
out so that it's
clear, that it makes
people curious and it
has clarity. So Ben
here has got the
white Google box on
a darker background, which
gives it contrast. Damien
here has got his
gold popping. So that
gives it contrast against
the dark background. Although
his white T -shirt
is competing there. Leila
Hormozi has got this
bright yellow and then
her hair are two
points of high contrast.
So she's sticking out
from that background. Now,
I've edited these to
wreck the contrast. And
you can see what
happens. So what happens
on this one, it
doesn't quite ruin the
image. Now the highest
point of contrast is
these. So these stick
out. In this one,
I've removed Damien's T
-shirt. So now only
this sticks out. And
in this one, I
took away the yellow.
And you'll probably notice
that Leila doesn't stick
out as much. So
we can use color.
We can use shade
to create contrast. The
next one is space.
Pay attention to this
one because you guys
always submit thumbnails that
ignore it. So a
thumbnail shouldn't look like
this. We don't want
to waste all of
this space, right? But
at the same time,
we don't want it
to be really crowded
where everything's just jammed
in together. And we
also don't want to
space out letters. So
these big dirty lines
in between. So when
you use Photoshop, the
default is to space
text out like this.
Keep an eye on
that. What we want
really is our text.
So there's some gap
between here, but also
we've got a bit
of a frame around
the edge, so it's
not too close to
everything and it's easy
to read. And you
can see there's almost
like an imaginary frame
around this text, right?
So if we look
at space, that's what
we started with. I
made myself bigger to
fill that horrible gap.
And then the text
pops a lot more
too. So here's a
thumbnail that is actually
from Andrej Zik's channel.
The thing I don't
like about this one
is this is the
highest point of contrast.
It's bright white.
So it's a waste
of space. So we
actually blew it up
a little bit to
fill that gap. And
I think that's a
better thumbnail. So space
is about making sure
there's not too much
space and things aren't
too crowded so that
your hero's face is
not too big.
So we've got a
little bit of color
here. And then there's
color. So just think
about color like this.
Buyers of different ages
are gonna like different
things and are gonna
have different expectations. So
if you design your
thumbnails with super bright
colors and make them
look like a radioactive
oil spill so things
are glowing,
it tracks bros, cryptos
and kids.
So when you're doing
your research, I'll teach
you later, you're gonna
do it. You're going
to see millions of
views attached to videos
like this. You need
to ask yourself, does
my 45 -year -old
female avatar want that?
The answer is probably
no. The next thing
you want to think
about is like the
millennial age. What you
tend to see on
YouTube is they like
this more authentic, more
muted tones, right? So
these are the exact
opposite. They're not in
your face. They're not
packed full of e
-numbers. They're kind of
simple. So we then
have the boomers. Sorry
to call you that.
I hate that word,
but that's what you
guys are called apparently.
Again, like more muted
tones, simpler designs, more
authentic. So different ages
like different designs. And
that's often one of
the mistakes people make
with color is they
go over the top
of it. Next thing
you want to be
thinking about for a
design is sex. Sorry.
So men appeal to
this shouty, sweary, angry
looking face. Women do
not. Women love actually
more cluttered thumbnails that
break way more of
my rules. Softer lighting,
more pastel shades. They
often like less contrast,
right? So although I've
just told you... All
of these design rules,
you've got to remember,
sometimes we're gonna have
to break them and
we're going to test.
And based on the
research you do, you're
going to try things
that maybe go against
some of these rules,
but we still need
to test. And then
we have text. So
you need to understand
that YouTube funnels are
not another title. What
we want is a
max of four words,
because look how long
that takes to read.
Now you can sneak
in five maybe, but
four is kind of
the most I go
for. Okay. So the
next thing is like,
do you put the
text on two lines
or three? And. You
just want to keep
in mind space. So
if you put the
text on two lines
like this, you've got
this big space here,
big space here, and
you might find it's
better to have it
on three lines like
that. After that, there's
our fonts. The first
thing you need to
realize is font size
matters. So look at
this. We've got this
horrible gap here. What
that means is, and
it's annoying because certain
words are long and
then certain words are
small. So we often
get this ugly kind
of look in our
thumbnails that doesn't make
it optimum for reading.
So what I like
to do is what
I call. B. Boxing
where I just make
each line of text
the same width and
it makes it so
much easier to read.
The other thing you
need to consider here
is you got to
use just one font
style. So although this
looks cool, the readability
takes a hit. And
one thing you need
to consider if you
are a branding person
is that readability is
more important than branding.
Just because your business
uses a certain font.
If it doesn't work
in a funnel, don't
use it. The whole
point is you're here
to grow your business.
So these are some
fonts I recommend. I've
used pop in a
monster. For years. They're
nice and bold. They're
easy to read, but
you're probably thinking, hang
on a sec, Ed
loads of people use
different fonts. Stop arguing
me. All right.
Well, of course, because
this is a whole
game of testing what
works. So if over
time you're posting and
you're like, I've found
a style and two
fonts do work, we
keep doing it. The
next thing you want
to be thinking about
is like these little
arrows and circles. You'll
see them over YouTube
for years, but they're
great for pointing out
a result or getting
viewers eyes to look
at the thing. They're
great for pointing out
a result or getting
viewers eyes to look
at the thing. But
if you're looking for
something that we think
matters the most to
them, right? The hero.
So you'll see them
a lot on YouTube.
Don't just throw them
in Willy nilly because
you think you need
them. But if you
ever want to get
someone's attention, an arrow
is a really good
way to do it.
And then the next
thing about fun design
is hierarchy. So this
is really important. So
read this. You read
this line and then
you read this and
then you read that
and then you go
up here because of
the different font sizes.
And this is known
as hierarchy. Hierarchy is
all about how you
position things and size
them to get attention.
And that's why we
keep doing this. We
cannot design thumbnails that
look like this. This
thumbnail has no hierarchy
at all. Everything is
crammed. The colors are
crazy. Nothing sticks out.
So if we look
at these images here
in terms of hierarchy,
the gold is the
first thing that sticks
out. Layla's the first
thing that sticks out.
The Google thing is
the first thing that
sticks out because the
image has been designed.
So the most important
thing sticks out first.
Now, when you are
designing thumbnails, if you
are using screenshots and
so on, most people
will turn around and
be like, I'm going
to put a stripe
down. I'm going to
put a dashboard in
my phone. But it
sucks, right? Because the
viewers can't see that.
So sometimes we have
to edit things like
screenshots that we put
into our image to
make sure that she
stick out. So you
can see here I
colored underneath the graph
purple. I made this
text much bigger. I
made the cells bigger.
So it gives context,
creates curiosity and the
hierarchy works. And then
we have emotion.
Don't do that. Like
this is dead. Even
Mr. Beast tested this
and found that if
he has his mouth
open in videos now,
he don't get as
many clicks. So his
videos are way more
serious. So for emotion,
just do a few
things. Smile, be pan.
You can look a
bit confused, a little
bit surprised. But don't
make a face you
wouldn't ever make in
person. I can't imagine
you ever go.
But also think about
how you use emotion.
So if I made
a video with why
I'm always happy and
then that is what
I look like. That
makes sense, right? The
video is about being
happy. I should be
smiling. So if we
have a positive title
or a positive thumbnail
or positive topic, use
a positive emotion. If
it's mistakes, use a
negative one. Or just
be pan all the
time. But your emotion
really needs to match
the packaging of the
video. So it's not
random. And then really
with design, just keep
things simple. Don't fall
into the trap of
thinking you need to
make these really cinematic
creative thumbnails. The simpler
the better, especially if
you're not great at
design. The thing is,
should you be in
your image or out
of it? Well, for
years, until I had
about 250 ,000 subscribers
on Film Booth, I
found that my face
in the thumbnail generally
didn't help it perform
as well. And then
after, I was like,
oh, I'm going to
make a video. It
helped it perform as
well. Having said that,
my best performing video
of all time had
my face in, but
it was covered by
money. So the general
rule of thumb is,
cold viewers don't care
about your face. Warm
viewers do. So what
do we do? We
can test stuff. So
some of you might
want to try thumbnails
that you're not in
and thumbnails that you
are in to work
out what's the best
direction. Now, let's move
on to a few
thumbnail mistakes you've got
to avoid. So the
first thing's first is
a visual metaphor. If
you ask AI to
design you a thumbnail
and you say, this
video is about a
roadmap for success, it's
going to tell you
to use a visual
metaphor.
Don't ever do that,
right? Thumbnails are monkey
brain. We need to
make viewers instantly go,
oh, well, this looks
interesting. And if we
give them a map
where they're like, wait,
what's this? I have
to work it out.
A roadmap to success.
Wait, what's this about?
What's this compass thing?
It doesn't work. Okay.
And then this is
an example of a
visual metaphor not working.
So unlock global clients.
And then the image
is a key, some
doors opened, and then
the world. People aren't
going to look at
that image, which they
look at first and
go, oh, this is
a visual metaphor. Oh,
cool. That's going to
help me unlock global
clients. They're going to
go key door earth.
Huh? Ain't going to
click. So you need
to avoid visual metaphors
all the time. You
also want to avoid
being overly creative. It's
nearly killed me and
James. But for six
months on Film Booth,
we were like, let's
just come up with
the most creative, amazing
looking art thumbnails we
can possibly do. And
every single one was
a flop. We always
had to go back
to the back up.
And we just realized
effects like this giant
money stuff that looks
kind of cool and
fun doesn't work on
YouTube. It almost makes
people think too hard.
Another thing is stock.
They just don't use
stock images. They cheap.
They're cheesy. If someone
sees the traditional like
man in a suit
shaking someone's hand thing,
they just look and
go, oh, this is
corporate nonsense. So avoid
cheesy stock images. Oh,
yeah. Here's another example
of overly creative, like
blew my mind with
a head exploding. The
viewers going, well, is
this about headaches? Like,
why is that man's
head on fire? I
blew my mind. Well,
it don't work. So
avoid anything that's too
creative. Sadly, the next
one is called an
inside joke. This is
really important. This is
an actual thumbnail I
made years ago.
And the reason there
is a shotgun in
the thumbnail about music
laws simplified is because
in the video about
a minute in, I
made a joke about
a shotgun. Well, if
the viewers haven't clicked
it, they don't know
that this is relevant
to the video. So
I call this the
inside joke. It's when
you put something in
your thumbnail, the viewers
will only understand if
they watch it. And
people do this all
the time. They're like,
I put an apple
in the thumbnail because
I use a metaphor
of an apple a
minute in. It's like,
well, they don't know
that. So never make
the inside joke. And
the other thing to
avoid is exact copies.
So this guy is
basically, as you can
see, just copying my
designs and the thumbnails.
And he's doing a
very good job of
imitating me. This is
kind of what you
get taught to do
on YouTube. The problem
is you don't want
to look like a
cheap imitation. So you
have to keep in
mind this guy's viewers
watch me. They're also
YouTube creators. So they're
going to go, that's
Ed's thumbnail. And they're
going to go, uh,
a knockoff. So we
don't want to look
like knockoffs. We want
to take what works
and design it in
a way that looks
unique to us while
still keeping the elements
that can get results.
The next thing is
like, just don't go
beyond your talent. My
thumbnail course will teach
you how to make
this thumbnail. It took
me and James three
hours to photograph it.
It's too much. Like
Nick is an amazingly
talented guy. This guy's
a talented photographer. So
is this lady. But
they're artists at the
end of the day.
And if you're not,
don't attempt these thumbnails.
They're only going to
backfire because you need
years of experience. The
other thing to avoid
is obviously AI. So
I stopped using the
AI for my thumbnails
because I noticed people
weren't liking it. My
viewers didn't seem to
want AI. But on
the other side of
this, some channels, their
viewers seem to really
like AI. Like Wes's
thumbnails are all AI
and they look great.
He's doing really well.
So just keep that
in mind. Like, although
I'm going to teach
these AI to make
thumbnails, it might not
be the right thing
for you if they
look too overly AI.
All right. And then
the next thing is
just making sure you
match your viewers. So
you can see that
the viewers are matching
their viewers expectations once
they've clicked. So when
Charlie was getting less
views, you know, he
was making these sort
of thumbnails. But he's
making this sort of
content inside. So we've
got high production whiteboard
inside. Don't really work,
right? He switches his
thumbnails to this. Then
the content looks very
similar. It matches the
expectations of the click.
So we can see
Layla here. She's got
this really authentic thumbnail.
You click play. She's
basically in the same
room. So the expectations
are matched. And then
we have Mark here.
He's got this book
thumbnail. The opening shot,
he's surrounded by books.
It's matching expectations. So
your thumbnail quality and
your video quality must
match. If we come
up with something slick
like that and then
we shot in a
webcam looking crap like
this, it's a no
-go. So really what
you should do with
thumbnails is just start
very simple and bolt
on complexity if your
viewers require it. All
right. So let's just
do a quick rundown
of everything we've learned
here and look at
the strategies and how
they're making things work.
So this is a
thumbnail. The strategy they're
using is the result
because it says sell
literally anything, the result
people want. The context
is there straight away
because of the word
sell. It's clear because
the text has got
nothing competing against it.
And it's making me
curious because I'm wondering
how do I sell
anything. So it's a
nice simple thumbnail that
works. Then we have
this one from Trey
from Talent House. This
is Trey's first video
he made after doing
my program. It got
2 million views. It's
a brilliant video. So
the strategy he's using
is curiosity because it
says do this every
day. It makes me
go what? Do what?
The context is the
guitar because we can
see the fretboard, right?
Right. It's clear because
well there's nothing competing
of the attention, right?
And it makes us
curious because this is
sticking out straight away
and this. Then we
have Matt. So Matt's
got a very different
strategy, high production. Strategy
is the result and
the result is working
less. The context is
given by work less
and the fact that
he's working in a
kitchen. It's clear because
although there's a lot
going on here and
it's kind of busy,
this is pretty simple
to read. It makes
me curious. How do
I work less and
earn more? And then
we have this video.
The strategy is curiosity.
It says liar. That
hooks you, right? Like
why is it a
liar? She looks shocked.
The context of the
topic is the food
bowl. This is going
to be something about
dieting or eating. It's
very clear because there's
high contrast on the
text, high contrast on
her. All the elements
are sticking out. There's
no clutter and it
makes you curious. But
Ed, I've seen the
opposite of all this
stuff work. Yes, of
course, because sometimes your
viewers will like things
to be broken. So
we use these rules
as a benchmark and
then we build on
it using our MVP
system. Let's start with
him. Okay, hold on.